<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-05-02T14:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Learning to use FICS - Freechess.org</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2014/05/03/How-to-use-FICS.html"/>
    <id>/blog/2014/05/03/How-to-use-FICS.html</id>
    <published>2014-05-02T14:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-05-02T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.freechess.org"&gt;Free Internet Chess Server - FICS -&lt;/a&gt; is the place where I learnt to play chess online.  It will always be free to play and use all the features, which are many. However this is not always obvious to newcomers.  &lt;strong&gt;FICS is full of great players, people and training - &lt;em&gt;if you know how to use it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  This post aims to explain how to get started on FICS.  </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.freechess.org"&gt;Free Internet Chess Server - FICS -&lt;/a&gt; is the place where I learnt to play chess online.  It will always be free to play and use all the features, which are many. However this is not always obvious to newcomers.  &lt;strong&gt;FICS is full of great players, people and training - &lt;em&gt;if you know how to use it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  This post aims to explain how to get started on FICS.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because FICS is a server and not a website like &lt;a href="http://www.chess.com"&gt;Chess.com&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.lichess.org"&gt;Lichess.org&lt;/a&gt; - you need a program to  use it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on which operating system you have, there are different programs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Programs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve preferred three programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.babaschess.net/default.asp"&gt;Babas Chess&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Babas Chess screenshot" width="777" height="494" src="/images/../images/Babaschess.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babas is GUI driven with tons of options.  Install and run it and follow the prompts and you will end up a screen resembling the above.  From here you can explore all sorts of options in &lt;code&gt;File &amp;gt; Preferences&lt;/code&gt; or just hit the &lt;code&gt;Quick Commands&lt;/code&gt; menu item and play some chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On FICS there is a channel 1 for &lt;strong&gt;general help&lt;/strong&gt; and channel 6 for &lt;strong&gt;interface help&lt;/strong&gt; where you can ask for help or just Google.  Your mileage with Babas may vary but it is certainly popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wish to run Babaschess on Linux or Mac OS X - use the awesome &lt;a href="https://www.winehq.org/"&gt;Wine&lt;/a&gt; and turn off sounds and emoticons if they give you crashes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="http://thief.sourceforge.net/download.html"&gt;Thief&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Thief screenshot" width="1546" height="988" src="/images/../images/Thief.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thief is dominant among &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bughouse_chess"&gt;Bughouse&lt;/a&gt; players and requires a bit more knowledge of FICS and commmands.  However with a bit of experimenting and Googling it is simple enough to use. If you like the look of bughouse chess - which is awesome in real-life - check out &lt;a href="http://www.bughouse.net/"&gt;Bughouse.net&lt;/a&gt; or channel 22 on FICS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thief is also Windows native but can run on Linux and Mac OS X using Wine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href="https://code.google.com/p/raptor-chess-interface/"&gt;Raptor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Raptor screenshot" width="1554" height="987" src="/images/../images/Raptor.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raptor is a newer Java based interface written by members of FICS. It runs on all operating systems and is quite popular among Mac OS X and Linux users.  However, it works just fine on Windows as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The configuration of Raptor can be extensive and &lt;a href="https://code.google.com/p/raptor-chess-interface/wiki/NewToRaptor"&gt;a visit to the homepage linked above is good idea for further documentation&lt;/a&gt;.  There are also &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Gorgonian"&gt;reviews around the Web&lt;/a&gt; to see how others configure and &lt;a href="https://code.google.com/p/raptor-chess-interface/wiki/UsefulTips"&gt;use Raptor well&lt;/a&gt;.  My setup is the screenshot above :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Registering on FICS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://code.google.com/p/raptor-chess-interface/wiki/NewToFics"&gt;best getting started guide&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="http://www.freechess.org/Register/"&gt;FICS&lt;/a&gt; has already been written by the friendly Raptor guys.  Download Raptor and follow along for screen by screen explanations!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Ongoing Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FICS&lt;/strong&gt; is a great place to play the variants of chess; bughouse, atomic, losers, suicide.  It is also a great community for strong blitz, tournaments in channel 49 and long time controls in Teamleague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However I found it necessary to to use other sites such as &lt;a href="http://chesstempo.com/"&gt;Chesstempo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chesspub.com/cgi-bin/chess/YaBB.pl"&gt;ChessPub&lt;/a&gt; to learn beyond the basics of playing chess on FICS.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give them a shot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very first person I saw when I first joined FICS was the user &lt;code&gt;TioHoracio&lt;/code&gt;.  After observing and learning from his games I learnt that he regularly defeats International Masters(IM&amp;rsquo;s) in Over-The-Board(OTB) chess and on FICS.  This is the way I percieve the quality of FICS - hidden but valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FICS is a throwback to internet chess from years ago rather than the current internet.  It is still a place where you can make friends, learn from experts for free and play long series&amp;#39; of games - something I found horribly lacking on non-free sites.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My FICS handle is &lt;strong&gt;maeniel&lt;/strong&gt; so feel free to drop me a message, bitcoin massage, question or just say hi.  &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Site</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2013/01/01/new-site.html"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/01/01/new-site.html</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T14:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Oranje Chess has moved to a new site!  It has a new blog with my own stories about chess learning, resources and the progress to growth chess in Australian schools and communities.  Also, when it is in season, chess game analysis and coverage of &lt;strong&gt;local&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;national&lt;/strong&gt;, and international chess events. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Oranje Chess has moved to a new site!  It has a new blog with my own stories about chess learning, resources and the progress to growth chess in Australian schools and communities.  Also, when it is in season, chess game analysis and coverage of &lt;strong&gt;local&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;national&lt;/strong&gt;, and international chess events. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.tatasteelchess.com/"&gt;Wiik aan Zee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a new year upon us, there is plenty of international chess tourneys to watch if you like Grandmaster chess. Ongoing is the &lt;a href="http://www.tatasteelchess.com/"&gt;famous tourney from Wiik aan Zee, called Tata Steel&lt;/a&gt; which features dozens of the top GMs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.zurich-cc.com/"&gt;Zurich Chess Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also to come is the &lt;a href="http://www.zurich-cc.com/"&gt;Zurich Chess Challenge&lt;/a&gt; at the end of the month, which is the strongest chess tourney to date with an average rating of 2801!  World Champion Carlsen, Anand, Naka, Aronian are all
there, so check it out on &lt;a href="htttp://www.freechess.org"&gt;FICS&lt;/a&gt; or one of the many other chess sites like &lt;a href="http://www.chess.com"&gt;Chess.com&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://auschesschamps.com/"&gt;Australia Chess Championships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back at home, the Aussie chess championships were held at the start of the year and attracted a good mix of locals, including Queenslanders IM Stephen Solomon and Brodie McClymont, and internationals.  Have a look at some of the games as there was some real tactical fireworks.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;OranjeChess on Chess.com&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be starting a chess.com membership to provide games and analysis from, so all my own games are available and documenting how I go about using the site, among other resources, to play and improve chess largely for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all for now!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
